Finding Aid for the S. Charles Lee papers LSC.1384
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Photographs
  - Theatres
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Probably hoping to get a larger commission than just a theatre, Lee produced this perspective sketch of his concept for a theatre integrated with a bank and a retail store. The Los Angeles suburb of Lakewood was a post-war phenomenon where thousands of houses were built in record time to create an entirely new community. Lakewood needed everything for its shopping center - banks, stores, and of course, a motion picture theatre.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Marquee (Box 3, Folder 17)
      This night photo of the marquee with its neon strips and interior illuminated sign was taken as a publicity photo for Bevelite, the manufacturer of the removable letters used to spell out the names of the show and the stars on the marquee.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Aerial view (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Lakewood's shopping center in the foreground is surrounded by vacant fields. The houses of the new community are going up in the background. An older village, Quincy, at lower left, will soon be surrounded by the new town. Two blocks at left center are marked as designated for a City College.
    - Laurel Theatre., 1940-1941.; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 18)
      In this rendering, Lee develops a concept based on the curvilinear forms of Streamline Moderne. Using swags and garlands and leaf and shell motifs as well as an L monogram at the front of the marquee, Lee applies a vocabulary of images borrowed from the Regency style of early 19th century England to the Streamlined forms of 1930s architecture.
    - Leimert Theatre - Los Angeles, [Sunset?]. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lido Theatre. - Mexico City., 1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Diseno en perspectiva (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Lee's concept for a large theatre in Mexico City uses circular domed forms borrowed from the Arabic tradition in Spain and applies elaborate encrustations of Churrigueresque ornament typical of the Spanish Baroque around the monumental central entry, at the cornice line and to frame the windows. Elaborate finials top the parapets and the suggestion of a minaret can be seen on the right.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Perspective sketch (Box 4, Folder 2)
      This theatre, situated at Villa de Guadalupe, Montevideo 96 (a suburb of Mexico City) opened December 25, 1942, and is still in use.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Simple curving lines and a sumptuously draped curtain suggest an understated elegance. The wall pilasters conceal indirect lights. Large round translucent glass discs in the ceiling diffuse the light over the space.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Auditorium entrance (Box 4, Folder 2)
      A grandiose Art Deco Baroque design frames the entrance to the auditorium. The center panel appears to be leather or fabric, with a design of three maidens flying through the air, bearing bouquets of flowers. The foyer walls are wood veneer, with the flitches laid on in a mirror pattern, making long vertical stripes on the walls.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Auditorium side wall, murals (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Colorful murals set in fanciful round painted frames depict regional dances and garb of Old Mexico.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Exterior (Box 4, Folder 2)
      As built, the circular front kiosk and tower perform the function of advertising the theatre as a destination and display the posters for shows to passersby.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Construction (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Construction photos reveal the immense effort involved in constructing this very large building. Unlike counterparts in the United States that were being built of poured concrete using derricks and heavy machinery, this building in Mexico City in the 1940s was painstakingly constructed of brick that was then surfaced with stucco.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Exterior, side elevation (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The box office is housed in a round domed next to the entry. The buttresses on the wall at left are topped by pyramidal caps and crowned by finials.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Exterior, box office (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The domed box office is at street level, but the entry itself is reached by a broad flight of stairs. Setting the building on a podium with an entrance set well back from the street differs from the usual motion picture theatre in the United States which is entered at street level. The theatre is made more imposing, reflecting the cosmopolitan atmosphere of Mexico City and the more formal Mexican custom of spending the whole evening out, eating and dancing in the restaurant.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Perspective sketch, night (Box 4, Folder 2)
      This night view emphasizes the illuminated tower and a round illuminated kiosk in Streamline Moderne style that would serve to attract people to the theatre.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Ticket window, detail (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The box office ticket window is framed by cast stone detailing suggesting a theatre curtain drawn open. Below the window is a small sign giving the name of the architect and the date, a detail usually omitted on buildings in the United States.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Construction (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The outline of the building takes shape. An arcade and a sinuous curved wall form a courtyard beside the auditorium wall.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Construction (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The dome of the box office was also constructed of brick, using a technique probably brought to Spain by the Arabs.
    - Linda Vista Theatre. - Tepayac, Mexico City, DF, 1942; Restaurant patio (Box 4, Folder 2)
      The large sunken patio next to the auditorium was an extension of the restaurant inside. Here people could eat, drink and socialize and also watch people on the street, a favorite pastime in Mexico.
    - Loma Theatre. - San Diego, 1944-1946; Exterior (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Perhaps Lee's most utilitarian design, the Loma is essentially a large box set in a parking lot. This is a bare bones building constructed during wartime, probably to serve soldiers stationed in San Diego, one of the biggest military garrisons on the West Coast. Architectural details are virtually non-existent.
    - Loma Theatre. - San Diego, 1944-1946; Exterior (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Lee's design still puts the box office and sign with its canvas marquee at the sidewalk. They are connected to the entrance by a canvas canopy on poles. The porthole window and the pylon jutting up from the corner of the building are the only references to the Streamline Moderne style.
    - Lyceum Theatre. - San Francisco, 1935-1936; Remodel. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Mayfair Theatre. - Ventura, 1939-1940; Exterior (Box 4, Folder 5)
      The realized building is less dramatic, partially because it is sited on a prosaic small-town street. Nevertheless, [the theatre] retains the portholes and swooping form of the roofline. The pylon sign and the curving marquee command the corner site.
    - Mayfair Theatre. - Ventura, 1939-1940; Lounge (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Indirect lighting concealed in the ceiling cove, and over-scaled couches and a mirror lend a spacious, elegant feeling to the simple space.
    - Mayfair Theatre. - Ventura, 1939-1940; Auditorium (Box 4, Folder 5)
      The simple interior of the auditorium is enlivened by gently undulating walls that are abruptly interrupted by angular partitions that frame and enclose a pair of gigantic paintings of flowers flanking the proscenium.
    - Mayfair Theatre. - Ventura, 1939-1940; Perspective sketch (Box 4, Folder 5)
      This sleek Streamline Moderne design with portholes and a swooping roof almost seems ready to take off from its site and hover over the ground like a proverbial flying saucer.
    - Mexico City Theatres. - El Capitan, Tepeyac., 1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor section, auditorium (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Porthole windows accent the foyer wall decorated with giant mythological figures that appear to represent both European and ancient Mexican traditions.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, auditorium (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Lee combines circular and curved forms to render a space both imposing and elegant.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The concept shows a large sculpture, possibly a fountain (perhaps a version of the fountain in the Chapultepec Theatre), set in the curved space of the low-ceilinged foyer. A circular opening in the ceiling reveals the mezzanine above.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, foyer, 1. piso, view 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, restaurant (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Large-scale ceiling trusses, French doors leading to an outdoor dining space and dramatic hanging banners create a theatrical effect for this restaurant area which also features a dance floor.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, foyer, 2. piso, view 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The monumental space is focused on the larger than life-size figure sculpture, probably intended to be a fountain, flanked by curved walls decorated with abstract designs drawn from abstract art of the early twentieth century. Perhaps a study for the Chapultepec Theatre foyer sculpture.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Here, Lee works with rectangles and flat surfaces. The space is grandiose. The ceiling opening may indicate a large indirect lighting scheme or an opening to a mezzanine above.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor section, foyer? (Box 4, Folder 7)
      In this version (See 40715) the wall is paneled in wood veneer and the applied decoration is an abstract design inspired by contemporary art forms.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, galeria, view 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Curved walls are decorated with oversize plant motifs, which contrast with the central sculpture reminiscent of Mayan or Aztec sculpture.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor section, auditorium (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The side exit doors of the auditorium are embellished with heavy Baroque ornament, while the wall above is finished in wood veneer set in a pattern of squares. An elaborate sculpture of a horse riding on waves flanks the proscenium.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor section, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      This section (stairs at right) depicts niches for sculpture on the side wall of the auditorium or a foyer area.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, proscenium (Box 4, Folder 7)
      The auditorium clearly includes a stage, providing the opportunity for live performances to be integrated into the evening's entertainment. Gigantic wave-like forms decorate the side wall.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor section, auditorium (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Another version of the scheme (See 40716) depicts an elaborate cosmological vision of planets, moon, and stars above the auditorium exit doors and a fierce warrior on horseback framing the proscenium.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, restaurant (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Low vaulted spaces and a high-ceilinged space with exposed rafters create the atmosphere of Old Mexico in this space to be used for eating, drinking, and entertainment.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Lee did a number of renderings for theatres to be built in Mexico City in the 1940s. At least two, perhaps three, were actually built. Because they included restaurants and other entertainment areas besides the motion picture theatre they were grander than most of his designs in the United States. This rendering depicts a grand foyer with a mezzanine and gigantic pylons anchoring the staircases at both sides.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, restaurant (Box 4, Folder 7)
      This view show the integration of the two previous restaurant areas, the larger high-ceilinged space in the foreground. An orchestra plays for dancing within one of the vaulted areas, while couples dance on the dance floor in the foreground.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Perspective sketch, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Lee uses circular and spiral forms to create a grand semi-circular staircase to the mezzanine level. Pylons decorated with wave, shell and spiral designs support the mezzanine level above. A ceiling lamp composed of layers of circles accents the foyer ceiling.
    - Mexico Theatre. - Mexico, 1945; Watercolor perspective, foyer (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Lee proposes a dramatic succession of spaces. A two-story curvilinear arch drawn from Spanish Baroque forms frames the entrance to a grand foyer embellished with Spanish Baroque designs in relief. A broad staircase beneath a dramatically curved opening leads from the grand foyer into a one-story foyer area.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Lounge entry (Box 4, Folder 8)
      A hallway space, not a room, the lounge features a curved banquette and a set of drinking fountains set in a mirrored niche. A curvilinear ceiling panel conceals the indirect lighting.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Auditorium, sculpture detail (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The larger than life-size sculpture of hunter with a bow and his dog is sleek and heroic, in the style of Prometheus at Rockefeller Center or the work of Carl Milles (40819, 40819).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Auditorium, balcony (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Foyer entrance, lobby and lobby entrance to Huyler's (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The glass walls and doors of the foyer nearly erase the transition from the sidewalk to the interior of the theatre.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Drinking fountain (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Lee included a shorter drinking fountain, scaled for children. This was a new idea for the time.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Foyer, mural and seat (Box 4, Folder 8)
      All the elements in the rendering (40802) were realized in the building, although the spaces are necessarily compressed and the elements appear crowded. The scale and drama of each feature, the lighting panels, the entrance arch, the mezzanine walls and railing, the mural, and the giant cartouche above. Mirrored walls above the banquettes to the left and the right, with the mirrors set in a diamond pattern, enhance the complexity of the space, while at the same time enlarging it.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Perspective sketch, candy counter (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The design for the refreshment or candy counter includes and overhanging canopy with scalloped edges, a curved counter with a diamond-patterned base, and porthole windows in the wall above. A mural with ocean motifs was part of the original concept. The final design evolved into a cleaner Streamline Moderne design in both the foyer candy counter (40810) and the mezzanine drink bar (40815).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Facade (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The Miami Theatre in downtown Miami, Florida, was Lee's last major motion picture theatre in the grand tradition of the movie palaces of the 1920s and 1930s. After 1950, smaller neighborhood theatres and Drive-ins became more popular with the development of the suburbs. The Miami, however, was one of Lee's largest and most all-encompassing designs executed in the United States. The complex included not only a motion picture theatre, which included a legitimate stage but also a restaurant and a candy store, all in a downtown urban setting. In the design, which was largely executed as shown in the renderings, Lee married Baroque and Rococo elements with Streamline Moderne features, producing an unusually eclectic design. The renderings show murals with sea-life motifs, suggesting that Lee drew inspiration from seashell and wave forms for many aspects of the design, which may account for the Baroque and Rococo-appearing design elements. Although demolished, the theatre is o! ne of the most extensively documented in the S. Charles Lee Collection at UCLA.The design of the façade, with its diamond-patterned panels and ornate cartouche is echoed in the interior. On the left is Huyler's, a candy shop and restaurant that was part of the theatre complex. The narrow site and the height of the building to the rear reflect the two-tier balcony and the long narrow plan of the auditorium, a scheme that Lee had used in his first major theatre, the Tower Theatre in Los Angeles.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Facade detail (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The scale of the cartouche is indicated by the life-size cardboard figure posed beside it.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Projection room (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The projection room is state of the art for 1946.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Stair to mezzanine (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Executed almost exactly as shown in the rendering (40803), the final forms of the staircase arch and ceiling panels are better integrated than in the rendering. The bending mirrored walls increase the complexity of the space.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Foyer (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The curved shapes, the treatment of the staircase, the poster cases, and the recessed lighting panels correspond closely to the rendering (40801). A focal point of the space is the mural of the Western hemisphere framed by the national flags and figures representing its peoples (40813). Banquettes with mirrored walls above them, flank the auditorium entrance.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Huyler's sweet shop counter (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Transparent glass walls facing the sidewalk and the lobby integrate the shop with the activity going on outside. The display counter and its cabinets and drawers are sleek and cleanly designed, as are the curving lunch counter and its simple chairs. The traditional forms of the glass chandelier lend a touch of historicist elegance to the otherwise stark interior.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Mezzanine drink bar (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The mezzanine drink bar and adjacent spaces has a simpler, more streamlined look than the downstairs foyer. Mirrored walls set at oblique angles create a more complex and confusing space.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Stair to mezzanine (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The stair to the mezzanine and lower balcony was set off to the side of the foyer and was simply executed, probably because of the constraints of space on the ground floor.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Stair to balcony (Box 4, Folder 8)
      This view of the mezzanine staircase corresponds more closely to the perspective in the rendering (40803).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Auditorium rear (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The photograph shows that the auditorium design was extremely simple. It was the bands of indirect lighting running up the walls and across the ceiling as well as vertically along the side walls and underneath the rear ceilings that created the effect (40819).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Auditorium front (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The simple lines of the long narrow auditorium, its shape dictated by the urban lot, all lead the eye toward the proscenium, which is framed by bands of indirect lighting and flanked by large scale designs in relief. A sumptuous curtain hung in swags fills the upper portion of the proscenium, scaling the immense arch down to cinema size.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Poster case (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Set right on the sidewalk, the poster cases are large and sleek. They provide a glimpse of the show within to every passerby. Titles in both English and Spanish reflect Miami's Latin American population, which is also depicted in the mural in the foyer (40812, 40813).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Perspective sketch, foyer (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The grand entrance to the auditorium, the curved lines of the mezzanine, the delicate tracery of the metal railing and the signature recessed lighting panels were realized for the most part in the building. See 40812.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Box office (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The recessed lobby draws the moviegoer into the space with neon tube strips on the ceiling focusing on the entrance and with the walls of floor to ceiling glass. The glass walls allow a view of the interior which glows at night. The box office with its curvilinear shape, also illuminated, and its sleek walls, plays to the fantasy of the moviegoers.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Huyler's restaurant (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The restaurant, located on the second floor, achieves a more elegant look with its sculptural ceiling light panels and the curvilinear back of the banquette on the far wall. The softly curtained windows overlooking the street would have cast an inviting night-time glow.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Perspective sketch, foyer stair (Box 4, Folder 8)
      See 40816,40817. The curving lines and delicate tracery of the stair railing contrast with the heavily embellished stairway arch. Porthole windows, typical of the Streamline Moderne style, open up the staircase walls. A mural with sea-life motifs decorates the curved wall to the right of the staircase. The recessed lighting panels in the ceiling and the diamond-patterned mirrored walls echo similar features in the foyer.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Mural (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The focal point of the foyer is the mural at the auditorium entrance. The peoples and the flags of the countries of the Americas are ranged around a map of the continents. Even fruits and pets are included. It is clear that the theatre intended to attract Miami's Latin American community as well as English speakers.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Huyler's sweet shop (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Simple lines, recessed wall cabinets illuminated by indirect lighting, the butt-jointed glass display case and the recessed ceiling lighting were all new and fashionable design features of the Moderne of the 1930s and 1940s.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Huyler's entry from theatre (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Glass walls and a glass door invite the customers into Huyler's the adjacent restaurant and candy store.
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Foyer entrance (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Curving lines, recessed lighting and mirrored surfaces create an expanding space in the foyer entrance area. The wavy wall with a surface of vertical ribs adds a sleeker streamlined look to the space (see 40804).
    - Miami Theatre. - Miami, 1946-1947; Listening aid, crying room? (Box 4, Folder 8)
      The crying room, a feature of many theatres of the period, was a soundproof glass-walled viewing room for mothers with small children. Here the model demonstrates the audio device that transmitted sound to individual viewers. The acoustic tile on the walls began to be widely used in the 1940s and soon became ubiquitous.